<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Gert Stulp</title>
<link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.gertstulp.com/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.433</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Social mechanisms underlying whether people have children</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2024_toulouse.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Social mechanisms underlying whether people have children</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Institute for Advanced Study in Toulouse, France</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://www.iast.fr/11th-toulouse-economics-and-biology-workshop">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2024_06_04_TOULOUSE">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>I gave a talk on how the demographic transition relates to networks for the 11th Toulouse Economics and Biology Workshop - Inequality in Networks.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2024_toulouse.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Growing Up Together in Society (GUTS): A team science effort to predict societal trajectories in adolescence and young adulthood</title>
  <dc:creator>Eveline A. Crone, Thijs Bol, Barbara R. Braams, Mark de Rooij, Barbara Franke, Ingmar Franken, Valeria Gazzola, Berna Güroğlu, Hilde Huizenga, Hilleke Hulshoff Pol, Loes Keijsers, Christian Keysers, Lydia Krabbendam, Lucres Jansen, Arne Popma, Gert Stulp, Nienke van Atteveldt, Anna van Duijvenvoorde, René Veenstra</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Crone_Development.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Growing Up Together in Society (GUTS): A team science effort to predict societal trajectories in adolescence and young adulthood</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Developmental Cognitive Neuroscience</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Eveline A. Crone, Thijs Bol, Barbara R. Braams, Mark de Rooij, Barbara Franke, Ingmar Franken, Valeria Gazzola, Berna Güroğlu, Hilde Huizenga, Hilleke Hulshoff Pol, Loes Keijsers, Christian Keysers, Lydia Krabbendam, Lucres Jansen, Arne Popma, Gert Stulp, Nienke van Atteveldt, Anna van Duijvenvoorde, René Veenstra</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1878929324000641">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Our society faces a great diversity of opportunities for youth. The 10-year Growing Up Together in Society (GUTS) program has the long-term goal to understand which combination of measures best predict societal trajectories, such as school success, mental health, well-being, and developing a sense of belonging in society. Our leading hypothesis is that self-regulation is key to how adolescents successfully navigate the demands of contemporary society. We aim to test these questions using socio-economic, questionnaire (including experience sampling methods), behavioral, brain (fMRI, sMRI, EEG), hormonal, and genetic measures in four large cohorts including adolescents and young adults. Two cohorts are designed as test and replication cohorts to test the developmental trajectory of self-regulation, including adolescents of different socioeconomic status thereby bridging individual, family, and societal perspectives. The third cohort consists of an entire social network to examine how neural and self-regulatory development influences and is influenced by whom adolescents and young adults choose to interact with. The fourth cohort includes youth with early signs of antisocial and delinquent behavior to understand patterns of societal development in individuals at the extreme ends of self-regulation and societal participation, and examines pathways into and out of delinquency. We will complement the newly collected cohorts with data from existing large-scale population-based and case-control cohorts. The study is embedded in a transdisciplinary approach that engages stakeholders throughout the design stage, with a strong focus on citizen science and youth participation in study design, data collection, and interpretation of results, to ensure optimal translation to youth in society.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Crone_Development.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Combining the strengths of Dutch survey and register data in a data challenge to predict fertility (PreFer)</title>
  <dc:creator>Elizaveta Sivak, Paulina Pankowska, Adriënne Mendrik, Tom Emery, Javier Garcia-Bernardo, Seyit Höcük, Kasia Karpinska, Angelica Maineri, Joris Mulder, Malvina Nissim, Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Sivak_JCSS.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Combining the strengths of Dutch survey and register data in a data challenge to predict fertility (PreFer)</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Journal of Computational Social Science</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Elizaveta Sivak, Paulina Pankowska, Adriënne Mendrik, Tom Emery, Javier Garcia-Bernardo, Seyit Höcük, Kasia Karpinska, Angelica Maineri, Joris Mulder, Malvina Nissim, Gert Stulp</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s42001-024-00275-6">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>The social sciences have produced an impressive body of research on determinants of fertility outcomes, or whether and when people have children. However, the strength of these determinants and underlying theories are rarely evaluated on their predictive ability on new data. This prevents us from systematically comparing studies, hindering the evaluation and accumulation of knowledge. In this paper, we present two datasets which can be used to study the predictability of fertility outcomes in the Netherlands. One dataset is based on the LISS panel, a longitudinal survey which includes thousands of variables on a wide range of topics, including individual preferences and values. The other is based on the Dutch register data which lacks attitudinal data but includes detailed information about the life courses of millions of Dutch residents. We provide information about the datasets and the samples, and describe the fertility outcome of interest. We also introduce the fertility prediction data challenge PreFer which is based on these datasets and will start in Spring 2024. We outline the ways in which measuring the predictability of fertility outcomes using these datasets and combining their strengths in the data challenge can advance our understanding of fertility behaviour and computational social science. We further provide details for participants on how to take part in the data challenge.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Sivak_JCSS.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Capturing the Social Life of a Person by Integrating Experience-Sampling Methodology and Personal-Social-Network Assessments</title>
  <dc:creator>Marie Stadel, Laura F. Bringmann, Gert Stulp, Timon Elmer, Stijn Verdonck, Merijn Mestdagh, Marijtje A. J. van Duijn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Stadel_Advances.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Stadel, M., Bringmann, L. F., Stulp, G., Elmer, T., Verdonck, S., Mestdagh, M., &amp; van Duijn, M. A. J. (2024). . ** 7(2): 25152459241244745. https://doi.org/10.1177/25152459241244745 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/25152459241244745" target="_blank"><strong>Download</strong></a></p>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Capturing the Social Life of a Person by Integrating Experience-Sampling Methodology and Personal-Social-Network Assessments</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Advances in Methods and Practices in Psychological Science</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Marie Stadel, Laura F. Bringmann, Gert Stulp, Timon Elmer, Stijn Verdonck, Merijn Mestdagh, Marijtje A. J. van Duijn</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/25152459241244745">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>The daily social life of a person can be captured with different methodologies. Two methods that are especially promising are personal-social-network (PSN) data collection and experience-sampling methodology (ESM). Whereas PSN data collections ask participants to provide information on their social relationships and broader social environment, ESM studies collect intensive longitudinal data on social interactions in daily life using multiple short surveys per day. In combination, the two methods enable detailed insights into someone’s social life, including information on interactions with specific interaction partners from the personal network. Despite many potential uses of such data integration, there are few studies to date using the two methods in conjunction. This is likely due to their complexity and lack of software that allows capturing the full social life of someone while keeping the burden for participants and researchers sufficiently low. In this article, we report on the development of methodology and software for an ESM/PSN integration within the established ESM tool m-Path. We describe results of a first study using the developed tool that illustrate the feasibility of the proposed method combination and show that participants consider the assessments insightful. We further outline study-design choices and ethical considerations when combining the two methodologies. We hope to encourage applications of the presented methods in research and practice across different fields.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Stadel_Advances.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Explaining uncertainty in women’s fertility preferences</title>
  <dc:creator>Amke van Tintelen, Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Stulp_Heliyon.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Explaining uncertainty in women’s fertility preferences</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Heliyon</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Amke van Tintelen, Gert Stulp</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2405844024036417?via%3Dihub">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>People’s fertility preferences are often considered an important determinant of fertility. What is often neglected in studies of preferred fertility, is the uncertainty that people may have about their preferences. In this study, using data on Dutch women through the Longitudinal Internet studies for the Social Sciences (collected early 2018), we examined women’s fertility preferences and asked detailed questions about the certainty of these preferences. We also examined whether women agreed with their partner on preferred family size, and to what extent partner (dis)agreement shaped uncertainty. We show that Dutch women expressed much uncertainty about their fertility preferences, with only one-third feeling strongly about their preferences. Uncertainty strongly increased when women preferred higher numbers of children, whereas already having children reduced it. Women who wanted no children were most certain about their preference. Higher preferred family sizes also led to more disagreement with the partner about these preferences, and greater partner disagreement, in turn, led to more uncertainty. These findings imply that people are more likely to downgrade their fertility preferences than to increase them, as women are more certain about their preferences for lower numbers of children and are more open to family sizes below than above their preferred choice. Partner disagreement is often resolved by not having (more) children, lowering realised fertility. Hence, these findings provide another explanation for why many people have fewer children than desired.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Stulp_Heliyon.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>It’s All About Timing: Exploring Different Temporal Resolutions for Analyzing Digital-Phenotyping Data</title>
  <dc:creator>Langener, A. M., Stulp, G., Jacobson, N. C., Costanzo, A., Jagesar, R. R., Kas, M. J., &amp; Bringmann, L. F.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Langener_timing.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; It’s All About Timing: Exploring Different Temporal Resolutions for Analyzing Digital-Phenotyping Data</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Advances in Methods and Practices in Psychological Science</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Langener, A. M., Stulp, G., Jacobson, N. C., Costanzo, A., Jagesar, R. R., Kas, M. J., &amp; Bringmann, L. F.</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/25152459231202677">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>The use of smartphones and wearable sensors to passively collect data on behavior has great potential for better understanding psychological well-being and mental disorders with minimal burden. However, there are important methodological challenges that may hinder the widespread adoption of these passive measures. A crucial one is the issue of timescale: The chosen temporal resolution for summarizing and analyzing the data may affect how results are interpreted. Despite its importance, the choice of temporal resolution is rarely justified. In this study, we aim to improve current standards for analyzing digital-phenotyping data by addressing the time-related decisions faced by researchers. For illustrative purposes, we use data from 10 students whose behavior (e.g., GPS, app usage) was recorded for 28 days through the Behapp application on their mobile phones. In parallel, the participants actively answered questionnaires on their phones about their mood several times a day. We provide a walk-through on how to study different timescales by doing individualized correlation analyses and random-forest prediction models. By doing so, we demonstrate how choosing different resolutions can lead to different conclusions. Therefore, we propose conducting a multiverse analysis to investigate the consequences of choosing different temporal resolutions. This will improve current standards for analyzing digital-phenotyping data and may help combat the replications crisis caused in part by researchers making implicit decisions.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Langener_timing.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>FertNet: Process Data from the Social Networks and Fertility Survey</title>
  <dc:creator>Stulp, G.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_FertNet.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; FertNet: Process Data from the Social Networks and Fertility Survey</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>CRAN</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gert Stulp</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download package <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=FertNet">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>I’ve made minor changes to the FertNet package – the package developed to deal with the Social Networks and Fertility Study. The biggest change is that I updated the citation to include the paper describing the study.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Stulp, G. (2023). FertNet: Process data from the social networks and fertility survey. https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=FertNet.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The package is described here: &gt; Stulp, G. (2023). Describing the Dutch Social Networks and Fertility Study and how to process it. <em>Demographic Research</em> 49(19), 493-512. https://www.demographic-research.org/articles/volume/49/19 <a href="https://www.demographic-research.org/articles/volume/49/19" target="_blank"><strong>Download</strong></a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_FertNet.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/Rlogo.svg" medium="image" type="image/svg+xml"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Life history theory and human behaviour</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_schiermonnikoog.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Life history theory and human behaviour</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Herders Hut, Schiermonnikoog</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://www.rug.nl/research/ecology-and-evolution/phdcourses/lifehistorytheory?lang=en">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2024_Schiermonnikoog.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>I gave a talk on life history theory and human behaviour for a group of talented biology PhD-students. The location was exciting!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_schiermonnikoog.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Predicting Mood Based on the Social Context Measured Through the Experience Sampling Method, Digital Phenotyping, and Social Networks</title>
  <dc:creator>Anna M. Langener, Laura F. Bringmann, Martien J. Kas &amp; Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Langener_Mood.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Predicting Mood Based on the Social Context Measured Through the Experience Sampling Method, Digital Phenotyping, and Social Networks</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Administration and Policy in Mental Health and Mental Health Services Research</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Anna M. Langener, Laura F. Bringmann, Martien J. Kas &amp; Gert Stulp</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10488-023-01328-0">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Social interactions are essential for well-being. Therefore, researchers increasingly attempt to capture an individual’s social context to predict well-being, including mood. Different tools are used to measure various aspects of the social context. Digital phenotyping is a commonly used technology to assess a person’s social behavior objectively. The experience sampling method (ESM) can capture the subjective perception of specific interactions. Lastly, egocentric networks are often used to measure specific relationship characteristics. These different methods capture different aspects of the social context over different time scales that are related to well-being, and combining them may be necessary to improve the prediction of well-being. Yet, they have rarely been combined in previous research. To address this gap, our study investigates the predictive accuracy of mood based on the social context. We collected intensive within-person data from multiple passive and self-report sources over a 28–day period in a student sample (Participants: N = 11, ESM measures: N = 1313). We trained individualized random forest machine learning models, using different predictors included in each model summarized over different time scales. Our findings revealed that even when combining social interactions data using different methods, predictive accuracy of mood remained low. The average coefficient of determination over all participants was 0.06 for positive and negative affect and ranged from − 0.08 to 0.3, indicating a large amount of variance across people. Furthermore, the optimal set of predictors varied across participants; however, predicting mood using all predictors generally yielded the best predictions. While combining different predictors improved predictive accuracy of mood for most participants, our study highlights the need for further work using larger and more diverse samples to enhance the clinical utility of these predictive modeling approaches.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2024_Langener_Mood.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A data-driven approach shows that individuals’ characteristics are more important than their networks in predicting fertility preferences</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_RoySoc.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A data-driven approach shows that individuals’ characteristics are more important than their networks in predicting fertility preference</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Royal Society Open Science</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gert Stulp, Lars Top, Xiao Xu, Lisa Sivak</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.230988">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>People’s networks are considered key in explaining fertility outcomes—whether people want and have children. Existing research on social influences on fertility is limited because data often come from small networks or highly selective samples, only few network variables are considered, and the strength of network effects is not properly assessed. We use data from a representative sample of Dutch women reporting on over 18 000 relationships. A data-driven approach including many network characteristics accounted for 0 to 40% of the out-of-sample variation in different outcomes related to fertility preferences. Individual characteristics were more important for all outcomes than network variables. Network composition was also important, particularly those people in the network desiring children or those choosing to be childfree. Structural network characteristics, which feature prominently in social influence theories and are based on the relations between people in the networks, hardly mattered. We discuss to what extent our results provide support for different mechanisms of social influence, and the advantages and disadvantages of our data-driven approach in comparison to traditional approaches.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_RoySoc.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Introducing the PreFer data challenge and its potential for fertility research</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_ODISSEI_PREFER.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; ODISSEI lecture</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Rotterdam, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://odissei-data.nl/nl/2023/10/odissei-lezing-how-predictable-are-fertility-outcomes-introducing-the-prefer-data-challenge-and-its-potential-for-fertility-research/">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/ODISSEI_PreFer_Gert_Stulp.pdf">here</a></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-video-camera" aria-label="video-camera"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; There is a <a href="https://eur.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=addbcfb3-2803-4ad7-a175-b0d600f80a92">video!</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>In a data challenge, (teams of) researchers using the same dataset try to best predict a particular outcome. In several fields like computer vision, natural language processing, and healthcare, prediction data challenges led to substantial progress both in model development and problem understanding. However, data challenges and the focus on predictability are still rare in the social sciences.</p>
<p>In this talk, we present the Predicting Fertility data challenge (PreFer), a collaborative effort between the University of Groningen, ODISSEI, Eyra, and Centerdata, and the first data challenge in demography. Its central goal is to establish the current predictability of fertility outcomes – whether people have children – using two unique datasets: the LISS panel, a Dutch longitudinal survey, and Dutch population registry data.</p>
<p>We will discuss the design of the data challenge and how this data challenge can produce novel and robust insights into an important life outcome and advance fertility research. The challenge will be open to any interested (team) of researchers and during the talk we will also provide practical details (timeline, data, evaluation, etc.) for those who are interested in joining it.</p>
<p>If you’d like to learn more about PreFer and to be notified when the registration for the challenge opens, please send an email!</p>
<p>Here are pictures of me presenting with my old face: <img src="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/odissei_GS1.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/odissei_GS2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Fertility</category>
  <category>Prediction</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_ODISSEI_PREFER.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/prefer_small.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="86" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A data-driven approach shows that individuals’ characteristics are more important than their networks in predicting fertility preferences</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_DVD.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Dag van Demografie</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Utrecht, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://www.nvdemografie.nl/news/dutch-demography-day-2023-2/">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2023_DVD_Gert Stulp.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>People’s networks are considered key in explaining fertility outcomes–whether people want and have children. Existing research on social influences on fertility is limited because data often come from small networks or from highly-selective samples, only few network variables are considered, and the strength of network effects is not properly assessed. We use data from a representative sample of Dutch women reporting on over 18,000 relationships. A data-driven approach including many network characteristics accounted for 0 to 40% of the out-of-sample variation in different outcomes related to fertility preferences. Individual characteristics were more important for all outcomes than network variables. Network composition was also important, particularly those people in the network desiring children or those choosing to be childfree. Structural network characteristics, which feature prominently in social influence theories and are based on the relations between people in the networks, hardly mattered. We discuss to what extent our results provide support for different mechanisms of social influence, and the advantages and disadvantages of our data-driven approach in comparison to traditional approaches.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Fertility</category>
  <category>Networks</category>
  <category>Prediction</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_DVD.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A data-driven approach shows that individuals’ characteristics are more important than their networks in predicting fertility outcomes</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_ODISSEI.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; ODISSEI conference</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Utrecht, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://odissei-data.nl/en/2023/11/odissei-conference-for-social-science-in-the-netherlands-2023/">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2023_ODISSEI.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>Social influences on fertility behaviour are well-established. Individuals learn from, receive support from, and perceive pressure from people in their social network regarding having children. Previous research has focused on identifying specific network characteristics in small networks in relation to fertility. In this study, we take a comprehensive, data-driven approach to assess the impact of various network characteristics on people’s fertility outcomes. We use unique personal network data from Dutch women to predict different fertility outcomes and employ LASSO regression, which can handle the inclusion of multiple variables, prevent overfitting, and leads to sparse models including only the most important variables. Our models were able to explain between 0% and 40% of the out-of-sample variation in the different outcomes we used. Individual characteristics were more important for all outcomes than network variables. Network composition was also important, in particular, people in the network that wanted children and people that wanted to be childfree. Structural network characteristics, based on the relations between people in the networks, hardly mattered. We discuss to what extent our results provide support for different mechanisms of social influence, and the advantages and disadvantages of our data-driven approach in comparison to traditional approaches.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Fertility</category>
  <category>Networks</category>
  <category>Prediction</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_ODISSEI.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Testing the combination of Feeling Safe and peer counselling against formulation-based cognitive behaviour therapy to promote psychological wellbeing in people with persecutory delusions: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial (the Feeling Safe-NL Trial)</title>
  <dc:creator>Eva Tolmeijer, Felicity Waite, Louise Isham, Laura Bringmann, Robin Timmers, Arjan van den Berg, Hanneke Schuurmans, Anton B. P. (Tonnie) Staring, Paul de Bont, Rob van Grunsven, Gert Stulp, Ben Wijnen, Mark van der Gaag, Daniel Freeman, David van den Berg</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Tolmeijer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Testing the combination of Feeling Safe and peer counselling against formulation-based cognitive behaviour therapy to promote psychological wellbeing in people with persecutory delusions: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial (the Feeling Safe-NL Trial)</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Trials</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Eva Tolmeijer, Felicity Waite, Louise Isham, Laura Bringmann, Robin Timmers, Arjan van den Berg, Hanneke Schuurmans, Anton B. P. (Tonnie) Staring, Paul de Bont, Rob van Grunsven, Gert Stulp, Ben Wijnen, Mark van der Gaag, Daniel Freeman, David van den Berg</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13063-023-07661-x">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Background Persecutory delusions are strong threat beliefs about others’ negative intentions. They can have a major impact on patients’ day-to-day life. The Feeling Safe Programme is a new translational cognitive-behaviour therapy that helps patients modify threat beliefs and relearn safety by targeting key psychological causal factors. A different intervention approach, with growing international interest, is peer counselling to facilitate personal recovery. Combining these two approaches is a potential avenue to maximize patient outcomes. This combination of two different treatments will be tested as the Feeling Safe-NL Programme, which aims to promote psychological wellbeing. We will test whether Feeling Safe-NL is more effective and more cost-effective in improving mental wellbeing and reducing persecutory delusions than the current guideline intervention of formulation-based CBT for psychosis (CBTp).</p>
<p>Methods A single-blind parallel-group randomized controlled trial for 190 out-patients who experience persecutory delusions and low mental wellbeing. Patients will be randomized (1:1) to Feeling Safe-NL (Feeling Safe and peer counselling) or to formulation-based CBTp, both provided over a period of 6 months. Participants in both conditions are offered the possibility to self-monitor their recovery process. Blinded assessments will be conducted at 0, 6 (post-treatment), 12, and 18 months. The primary outcome is mental wellbeing. The overall effect over time (baseline to 18-month follow-up) and the effects at each timepoint will be determined. Secondary outcomes include the severity of the persecutory delusion, general paranoid ideation, patient-chosen therapy outcomes, and activity. Service use data and quality of life data will be collected for the health-economic evaluation.</p>
<p>Discussion The Feeling Safe-NL Trial is the first to evaluate a treatment for people with persecutory delusions, while using mental wellbeing as the primary outcome. It will also provide the first evaluation of the combination of a peer counselling intervention and a CBT-based program for recovery from persecutory delusions.</p>
<p>Trial registration Current Controlled Trials ISRCTN25766661 (retrospectively registered 7 July 2022).</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Tolmeijer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The secret sauce of data science</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_new_beginnings.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; New Beginnings Event - Expertise Social Sciences Health &amp; Well-being</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Groningen, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://www.rug.nl/gmw/expertise-centre-social-sciences-health-and-well-being/?lang=en">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/new_beginnings_gert_stulp.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>In this five minute talk, I argue that a focus on (out-of-sample) prediction will benefit the social sciences.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Prediction</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_new_beginnings.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>This mess we’re in? Or how simulation and prediction will advance the social sciences</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_Hasselt.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The Data Science Insitute, Hasselt University</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Hasselt, Belgium</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://www.uhasselt.be/en/instituten-en/dsi">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2023_Hasselt.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>Demography and sociology have produced a sophisticated body of work on fertility outcomes, i.e., whether, why, and when people have children. Such research has uncovered many characteristics underlying fertility. Unfortunately, traditional ways of statistical analyses means that results are difficult to compare across studies and that we have little understanding on the (relative) importance of these characteristics. In light of the credibility crisis that has taken hold of many other fields and disciplines, one might similarly worry about the robustness of findings in demography and sociology. In this talk I will argue and show that a focus on predictive ability and on microsimulation will advance fertility research and make it more reliable.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Fertility</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_Hasselt.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Describing the Dutch Social Networks and Fertility Study and how to process it</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_DR.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Describing the Dutch Social Networks and Fertility Study and how to process it</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Demographic Research</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gert Stulp</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://www.demographic-research.org/articles/volume/49/19">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p><strong>Background</strong>: The social networks of people play a prominent role in theories on fertility. Investigating how networks shape behaviour is hard, because of the difficulty in measuring (large) networks among representative samples. Therefore, comprehensive studies of the variation in the structure and composition of networks and their impact on fertility outcomes are lacking.</p>
<p><strong>Objective</strong>: I aim to, first, describe the Dutch Social Networks and Fertility Study, and, second, describe the R-package FertNet that processes data from this study and transforms it into an easy-to-use format for researchers.</p>
<p><strong>Methods</strong>: The data used are from the Longitudinal Internet Social Survey (LISS) panel, a representative panel of Dutch households. The focus is on the Social Networks and Fertility Study that includes a subsample of women between the ages of 18‒40. Specific survey software was designed to capture each respondent’s personal network comprising 25 individuals with whom they had a relationship. In total, 758 women reported on over 18,750 relationships. For each person with whom the respondent had a relationship, several questions were asked about fertility-related topics. Uniquely, the connections between these people were also assessed. The R-package FertNet corrects data issues and transforms unstructured network data into alter-attribute and alter-tie datasets that can be handled by a diversity of network analytical approaches.</p>
<p><strong>Contribution</strong>: The Social Networks and Fertility Study is a unique resource that allows for a comprehensive investigation of how networks shape fertility behaviour. It provides better estimates of network characteristics than earlier literature based on smaller networks. The R-package FertNet assists researchers in their analyses.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_DR.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Feedback About a Person’s Social Context - Personal Networks and Daily Social Interactions</title>
  <dc:creator>Marie Stadel, Gert Stulp, Anna M. Langener, Timon Elmer, Marijtje A. J. van Duijn &amp; Laura F. Bringmann</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stadel_Feedback.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Feedback About a Person’s Social Context - Personal Networks and Daily Social Interactions</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Administration and Policy in Mental Health and Mental Health Services Research</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Marie Stadel, Gert Stulp, Anna M. Langener, Timon Elmer, Marijtje A. J. van Duijn &amp; Laura F. Bringmann</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10488-023-01293-8">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>The social context of a person, meaning their social relationships and daily social interactions, is an important factor for understanding their mental health. However, personalised feedback approaches to psychotherapy do not consider this factor sufficiently yet. Therefore, we developed an interactive feedback prototype focusing specifically on a person’s social relationships as captured with personal social networks (PSN) and daily social interactions as captured with experience sampling methodology (ESM). We describe the development of the prototype as well as two evaluation studies: Semi-structured interviews with students (N = 23) and a focus group discussion with five psychotherapy patients. Participants from both studies considered the prototype useful. The students considered participation in our study, which included social context assessment via PSN and ESM as well as a feedback session, insightful. However, it remains unclear how much insight the feedback procedure generated for the students beyond the insights they already gained from the assessments. The focus group patients indicated that in a clinical context, (social context) feedback may be especially useful to generate insight for the clinician and facilitate collaboration between patient and clinician. Furthermore, it became clear that the current feedback prototype requires explanations by a researcher or trained clinician and cannot function as a stand-alone intervention. As such, we discuss our feedback prototype as a starting point for future research and clinical implementation.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stadel_Feedback.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Prediction in the social sciences</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/overview/prediction.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>The social sciences, understandably, focus on explaining and understanding phenomena. In traditional statistical models, “understanding” is typically achieved in the following way: A relatively small theoretical model is constructed (say, 5 variables), and associations between these variables are specified (typically drawn as arrows between variables in a model). Hypotheses often concern the strength of a particular arrow, which mostly comes down to whether this strength is different from zero (i.e., does X have an effect on Y given Z) in a sample, which in turn is mostly assessed through p-values. This approach has led and will lead to a sophisticated body of research, but it is not without problems. Whether an effect is non-zero or not is not particularly interesting; the p-value does not inform on whether an effect is important, and it is easy to ‘manipulate’ a p-value towards being below a magic threshold; good “in-sample models” may fail to predict unseen cases well. All of this means that even if we have a highly significant, non-zero effect, this does not necessarily mean we have good understanding.</p>
<p>This is why recent research has argued that explanatory modelling should be complemented by predictive modelling. That is, there is great benefit to focus on how well a model predicts cases that the model has not seen before. This prediction may be done through machine learning, but this is not the key point for me.</p>
<p>I hope that my (future) research will help in making this case clearly and convince social scientists of the advantages of taking out-of-sample prediction seriously and also how optimising this quantity can lead to increased understanding of the system.</p>
<section id="prefer" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="prefer">PreFer</h2>
<p>One of the main ways in which I hope to do this, is the Predicting Fertility data challenge <a href="https://preferdatachallenge.nl">PreFer</a>:</p>
<p><img src="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/PreFer_logo_LONG.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00705">Here</a> you can find a preprint of the challenge:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Sivak, E., Pankowska, P., Mendrik, A., Emery, T., Garcia-Bernardo, J., Hocuk, S., Karpinska, K., Maineri, A., Mulder, J., Nissim, M., and Stulp, G., 2024. Combining the Strengths of Dutch Survey and Register Data in a Data Challenge to Predict Fertility (PreFer). https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00705</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="related-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="related-content">Related content</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Stulp, G., Top, L., Xu, X., &amp; Sivak, E. (2023). A data-driven approach shows that individuals’ characteristics are more important than their networks in predicting fertility preferences. Royal Society Open Science 10(12), 230988. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.230988">https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.230988</a> [This is one of the studies where I use a data-driven approach to a sociological topic]</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Stulp, G., Verhagen, MD., Arpino, B. (submitted). A plea for reporting out-of-sample predictive accuracy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Langener, A. M., Bringmann, L. F., Kas, M. J., &amp; Stulp, G. (2024). Predicting Mood Based on the Social Context Measured Through the Experience Sampling Method, Digital Phenotyping, and Social Networks. <em>Administration and Policy in Mental Health and Mental Health Services Research</em>. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10488-023-01328-0 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10488-023-01328-0" target="_blank"><strong>Download</strong></a></p>
</blockquote>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Overview</category>
  <category>Prediction</category>
  <category>Machine learning</category>
  <category>Data science</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/overview/prediction.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/prediction.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="96" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Simulating the evolution of height in the Netherlands in recent history</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp, Tyler Bonnel, Louise Barrett</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_History.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Simulating the evolution of height in the Netherlands in recent history</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>The History of the Family</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gert Stulp, Tyler Bonnel, Louise Barrett</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1081602X.2023.2192193">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>The Dutch have a remarkable history when it comes to height. From being one of the shortest European populations in the 19th Century, the Dutch grew some 20 cm and are currently the tallest population in the world. Wealth, hygiene, and diet are well-established contributors to this major increase in height. Some have suggested that natural selection may also contribute to the trend, but evidence is weak. Here, we investigate the potential role of natural selection in the increase in height through simulations. We first ask what if natural selection was solely responsible for the observed increase in height? If the increase in average height was fully due to natural selection on male height, then across six consecutive generations, men who were two standard deviation above average height would need to have eight times more children on average. If selection acted only through those who have the opportunity to reproduce, then reproduction would need to be restricted to the tallest third (37%) of the population in order to give rise to the stark increase in height over time. No linear relationship between height and child mortality is able to account for the increase over time. We then present simulations based on previously observed estimates of partnership, mortality, selection and heritability and show that natural selection had a negligible effect (estimates from 0.07 to 0.36 cm) on the increase in height in the period 1850 to 2000. Our simulations highlight the plasticity of height and how remarkable the trend in height is in evolutionary terms. Only by using a combination of methods and insights from different disciplines, including biology, demography, and history are we potentially able to address how much of the increase in height is due to natural selection versus other causes.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_History.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
