<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Gert Stulp</title>
<link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.gertstulp.com/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.433</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Life history theory and human behaviour</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_schiermonnikoog.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Life history theory and human behaviour</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Herders Hut, Schiermonnikoog</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://www.rug.nl/research/ecology-and-evolution/phdcourses/lifehistorytheory?lang=en">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2024_Schiermonnikoog.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>I gave a talk on life history theory and human behaviour for a group of talented biology PhD-students. The location was exciting!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_schiermonnikoog.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A data-driven approach shows that individuals’ characteristics are more important than their networks in predicting fertility preferences</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_RoySoc.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A data-driven approach shows that individuals’ characteristics are more important than their networks in predicting fertility preference</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Royal Society Open Science</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gert Stulp, Lars Top, Xiao Xu, Lisa Sivak</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.230988">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>People’s networks are considered key in explaining fertility outcomes—whether people want and have children. Existing research on social influences on fertility is limited because data often come from small networks or highly selective samples, only few network variables are considered, and the strength of network effects is not properly assessed. We use data from a representative sample of Dutch women reporting on over 18 000 relationships. A data-driven approach including many network characteristics accounted for 0 to 40% of the out-of-sample variation in different outcomes related to fertility preferences. Individual characteristics were more important for all outcomes than network variables. Network composition was also important, particularly those people in the network desiring children or those choosing to be childfree. Structural network characteristics, which feature prominently in social influence theories and are based on the relations between people in the networks, hardly mattered. We discuss to what extent our results provide support for different mechanisms of social influence, and the advantages and disadvantages of our data-driven approach in comparison to traditional approaches.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_RoySoc.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Introducing the PreFer data challenge and its potential for fertility research</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_ODISSEI_PREFER.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; ODISSEI lecture</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Rotterdam, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://odissei-data.nl/nl/2023/10/odissei-lezing-how-predictable-are-fertility-outcomes-introducing-the-prefer-data-challenge-and-its-potential-for-fertility-research/">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/ODISSEI_PreFer_Gert_Stulp.pdf">here</a></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-video-camera" aria-label="video-camera"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; There is a <a href="https://eur.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=addbcfb3-2803-4ad7-a175-b0d600f80a92">video!</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>In a data challenge, (teams of) researchers using the same dataset try to best predict a particular outcome. In several fields like computer vision, natural language processing, and healthcare, prediction data challenges led to substantial progress both in model development and problem understanding. However, data challenges and the focus on predictability are still rare in the social sciences.</p>
<p>In this talk, we present the Predicting Fertility data challenge (PreFer), a collaborative effort between the University of Groningen, ODISSEI, Eyra, and Centerdata, and the first data challenge in demography. Its central goal is to establish the current predictability of fertility outcomes – whether people have children – using two unique datasets: the LISS panel, a Dutch longitudinal survey, and Dutch population registry data.</p>
<p>We will discuss the design of the data challenge and how this data challenge can produce novel and robust insights into an important life outcome and advance fertility research. The challenge will be open to any interested (team) of researchers and during the talk we will also provide practical details (timeline, data, evaluation, etc.) for those who are interested in joining it.</p>
<p>If you’d like to learn more about PreFer and to be notified when the registration for the challenge opens, please send an email!</p>
<p>Here are pictures of me presenting with my old face: <img src="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/odissei_GS1.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/odissei_GS2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Fertility</category>
  <category>Prediction</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_ODISSEI_PREFER.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/prefer_small.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="86" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A data-driven approach shows that individuals’ characteristics are more important than their networks in predicting fertility preferences</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_DVD.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Dag van Demografie</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Utrecht, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://www.nvdemografie.nl/news/dutch-demography-day-2023-2/">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2023_DVD_Gert Stulp.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>People’s networks are considered key in explaining fertility outcomes–whether people want and have children. Existing research on social influences on fertility is limited because data often come from small networks or from highly-selective samples, only few network variables are considered, and the strength of network effects is not properly assessed. We use data from a representative sample of Dutch women reporting on over 18,000 relationships. A data-driven approach including many network characteristics accounted for 0 to 40% of the out-of-sample variation in different outcomes related to fertility preferences. Individual characteristics were more important for all outcomes than network variables. Network composition was also important, particularly those people in the network desiring children or those choosing to be childfree. Structural network characteristics, which feature prominently in social influence theories and are based on the relations between people in the networks, hardly mattered. We discuss to what extent our results provide support for different mechanisms of social influence, and the advantages and disadvantages of our data-driven approach in comparison to traditional approaches.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Fertility</category>
  <category>Networks</category>
  <category>Prediction</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_DVD.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A data-driven approach shows that individuals’ characteristics are more important than their networks in predicting fertility outcomes</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_ODISSEI.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; ODISSEI conference</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Utrecht, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://odissei-data.nl/en/2023/11/odissei-conference-for-social-science-in-the-netherlands-2023/">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2023_ODISSEI.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>Social influences on fertility behaviour are well-established. Individuals learn from, receive support from, and perceive pressure from people in their social network regarding having children. Previous research has focused on identifying specific network characteristics in small networks in relation to fertility. In this study, we take a comprehensive, data-driven approach to assess the impact of various network characteristics on people’s fertility outcomes. We use unique personal network data from Dutch women to predict different fertility outcomes and employ LASSO regression, which can handle the inclusion of multiple variables, prevent overfitting, and leads to sparse models including only the most important variables. Our models were able to explain between 0% and 40% of the out-of-sample variation in the different outcomes we used. Individual characteristics were more important for all outcomes than network variables. Network composition was also important, in particular, people in the network that wanted children and people that wanted to be childfree. Structural network characteristics, based on the relations between people in the networks, hardly mattered. We discuss to what extent our results provide support for different mechanisms of social influence, and the advantages and disadvantages of our data-driven approach in comparison to traditional approaches.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Fertility</category>
  <category>Networks</category>
  <category>Prediction</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_ODISSEI.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Testing the combination of Feeling Safe and peer counselling against formulation-based cognitive behaviour therapy to promote psychological wellbeing in people with persecutory delusions: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial (the Feeling Safe-NL Trial)</title>
  <dc:creator>Eva Tolmeijer, Felicity Waite, Louise Isham, Laura Bringmann, Robin Timmers, Arjan van den Berg, Hanneke Schuurmans, Anton B. P. (Tonnie) Staring, Paul de Bont, Rob van Grunsven, Gert Stulp, Ben Wijnen, Mark van der Gaag, Daniel Freeman, David van den Berg</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Tolmeijer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Testing the combination of Feeling Safe and peer counselling against formulation-based cognitive behaviour therapy to promote psychological wellbeing in people with persecutory delusions: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial (the Feeling Safe-NL Trial)</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Trials</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Eva Tolmeijer, Felicity Waite, Louise Isham, Laura Bringmann, Robin Timmers, Arjan van den Berg, Hanneke Schuurmans, Anton B. P. (Tonnie) Staring, Paul de Bont, Rob van Grunsven, Gert Stulp, Ben Wijnen, Mark van der Gaag, Daniel Freeman, David van den Berg</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13063-023-07661-x">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Background Persecutory delusions are strong threat beliefs about others’ negative intentions. They can have a major impact on patients’ day-to-day life. The Feeling Safe Programme is a new translational cognitive-behaviour therapy that helps patients modify threat beliefs and relearn safety by targeting key psychological causal factors. A different intervention approach, with growing international interest, is peer counselling to facilitate personal recovery. Combining these two approaches is a potential avenue to maximize patient outcomes. This combination of two different treatments will be tested as the Feeling Safe-NL Programme, which aims to promote psychological wellbeing. We will test whether Feeling Safe-NL is more effective and more cost-effective in improving mental wellbeing and reducing persecutory delusions than the current guideline intervention of formulation-based CBT for psychosis (CBTp).</p>
<p>Methods A single-blind parallel-group randomized controlled trial for 190 out-patients who experience persecutory delusions and low mental wellbeing. Patients will be randomized (1:1) to Feeling Safe-NL (Feeling Safe and peer counselling) or to formulation-based CBTp, both provided over a period of 6 months. Participants in both conditions are offered the possibility to self-monitor their recovery process. Blinded assessments will be conducted at 0, 6 (post-treatment), 12, and 18 months. The primary outcome is mental wellbeing. The overall effect over time (baseline to 18-month follow-up) and the effects at each timepoint will be determined. Secondary outcomes include the severity of the persecutory delusion, general paranoid ideation, patient-chosen therapy outcomes, and activity. Service use data and quality of life data will be collected for the health-economic evaluation.</p>
<p>Discussion The Feeling Safe-NL Trial is the first to evaluate a treatment for people with persecutory delusions, while using mental wellbeing as the primary outcome. It will also provide the first evaluation of the combination of a peer counselling intervention and a CBT-based program for recovery from persecutory delusions.</p>
<p>Trial registration Current Controlled Trials ISRCTN25766661 (retrospectively registered 7 July 2022).</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Tolmeijer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The secret sauce of data science</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_new_beginnings.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; New Beginnings Event - Expertise Social Sciences Health &amp; Well-being</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Groningen, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://www.rug.nl/gmw/expertise-centre-social-sciences-health-and-well-being/?lang=en">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/new_beginnings_gert_stulp.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>In this five minute talk, I argue that a focus on (out-of-sample) prediction will benefit the social sciences.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Prediction</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_new_beginnings.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>This mess we’re in? Or how simulation and prediction will advance the social sciences</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_Hasselt.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The Data Science Insitute, Hasselt University</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Hasselt, Belgium</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://www.uhasselt.be/en/instituten-en/dsi">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2023_Hasselt.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>Demography and sociology have produced a sophisticated body of work on fertility outcomes, i.e., whether, why, and when people have children. Such research has uncovered many characteristics underlying fertility. Unfortunately, traditional ways of statistical analyses means that results are difficult to compare across studies and that we have little understanding on the (relative) importance of these characteristics. In light of the credibility crisis that has taken hold of many other fields and disciplines, one might similarly worry about the robustness of findings in demography and sociology. In this talk I will argue and show that a focus on predictive ability and on microsimulation will advance fertility research and make it more reliable.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Fertility</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_Hasselt.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Describing the Dutch Social Networks and Fertility Study and how to process it</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_DR.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Describing the Dutch Social Networks and Fertility Study and how to process it</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Demographic Research</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gert Stulp</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://www.demographic-research.org/articles/volume/49/19">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p><strong>Background</strong>: The social networks of people play a prominent role in theories on fertility. Investigating how networks shape behaviour is hard, because of the difficulty in measuring (large) networks among representative samples. Therefore, comprehensive studies of the variation in the structure and composition of networks and their impact on fertility outcomes are lacking.</p>
<p><strong>Objective</strong>: I aim to, first, describe the Dutch Social Networks and Fertility Study, and, second, describe the R-package FertNet that processes data from this study and transforms it into an easy-to-use format for researchers.</p>
<p><strong>Methods</strong>: The data used are from the Longitudinal Internet Social Survey (LISS) panel, a representative panel of Dutch households. The focus is on the Social Networks and Fertility Study that includes a subsample of women between the ages of 18‒40. Specific survey software was designed to capture each respondent’s personal network comprising 25 individuals with whom they had a relationship. In total, 758 women reported on over 18,750 relationships. For each person with whom the respondent had a relationship, several questions were asked about fertility-related topics. Uniquely, the connections between these people were also assessed. The R-package FertNet corrects data issues and transforms unstructured network data into alter-attribute and alter-tie datasets that can be handled by a diversity of network analytical approaches.</p>
<p><strong>Contribution</strong>: The Social Networks and Fertility Study is a unique resource that allows for a comprehensive investigation of how networks shape fertility behaviour. It provides better estimates of network characteristics than earlier literature based on smaller networks. The R-package FertNet assists researchers in their analyses.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_DR.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Prediction in the social sciences</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/overview/prediction.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






 ]]></description>
  <category>Overview</category>
  <category>Prediction</category>
  <category>Machine learning</category>
  <category>Data science</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/overview/prediction.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/prediction.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="96" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Simulating the evolution of height in the Netherlands in recent history</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp, Tyler Bonnel, Louise Barrett</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_History.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Simulating the evolution of height in the Netherlands in recent history</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>The History of the Family</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gert Stulp, Tyler Bonnel, Louise Barrett</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1081602X.2023.2192193">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>The Dutch have a remarkable history when it comes to height. From being one of the shortest European populations in the 19th Century, the Dutch grew some 20 cm and are currently the tallest population in the world. Wealth, hygiene, and diet are well-established contributors to this major increase in height. Some have suggested that natural selection may also contribute to the trend, but evidence is weak. Here, we investigate the potential role of natural selection in the increase in height through simulations. We first ask what if natural selection was solely responsible for the observed increase in height? If the increase in average height was fully due to natural selection on male height, then across six consecutive generations, men who were two standard deviation above average height would need to have eight times more children on average. If selection acted only through those who have the opportunity to reproduce, then reproduction would need to be restricted to the tallest third (37%) of the population in order to give rise to the stark increase in height over time. No linear relationship between height and child mortality is able to account for the increase over time. We then present simulations based on previously observed estimates of partnership, mortality, selection and heritability and show that natural selection had a negligible effect (estimates from 0.07 to 0.36 cm) on the increase in height in the period 1850 to 2000. Our simulations highlight the plasticity of height and how remarkable the trend in height is in evolutionary terms. Only by using a combination of methods and insights from different disciplines, including biology, demography, and history are we potentially able to address how much of the increase in height is due to natural selection versus other causes.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_History.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>FertNet: Process Data from the Social Networks and Fertility Survey</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_FertNet.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; FertNet: Process Data from the Social Networks and Fertility Survey</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>CRAN</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gert Stulp</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/FertNet/index.html">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Processes data from The Social Networks and Fertility Survey, downloaded from <a href="https://dataarchive.lissdata.nl" class="uri">https://dataarchive.lissdata.nl</a>, including correcting respondent errors and transforming network data into network objects to facilitate analyses and visualisation.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Stulp_FertNet.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Capturing the Dynamics of the Social Environment Through Experience Sampling Methods, Passive Sensing, and Egocentric Networks: Scoping Review</title>
  <dc:creator>Anna Langener, Gert Stulp, Martien Kas, Laura Bringmann</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Langener_JMIR.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Capturing the Dynamics of the Social Environment Through Experience Sampling Methods, Passive Sensing, and Egocentric Networks: Scoping Review</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>JMIR Mental Health</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Anna Langener, Gert Stulp, Martien Kas, Laura Bringmann</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://mental.jmir.org/2023/1/e42646">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Background: Social interactions are important for well-being, and therefore, researchers are increasingly attempting to capture people’s social environment. Many different disciplines have developed tools to measure the social environment, which can be highly variable over time. The experience sampling method (ESM) is often used in psychology to study the dynamics within a person and the social environment. In addition, passive sensing is often used to capture social behavior via sensors from smartphones or other wearable devices. Furthermore, sociologists use egocentric networks to track how social relationships are changing. Each of these methods is likely to tap into different but important parts of people’s social environment. Thus far, the development and implementation of these methods have occurred mostly separately from each other. Objective: Our aim was to synthesize the literature on how these methods are currently used to capture the changing social environment in relation to well-being and assess how to best combine these methods to study well-being. Methods: We conducted a scoping review according to the PRISMA (Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses) guidelines. Results: We included 275 studies. In total, 3 important points follow from our review. First, each method captures a different but important part of the social environment at a different temporal resolution. Second, measures are rarely validated (&gt;70% of ESM studies and 50% of passive sensing studies were not validated), which undermines the robustness of the conclusions drawn. Third, a combination of methods is currently lacking (only 15/275, 5.5% of the studies combined ESM and passive sensing, and no studies combined all 3 methods) but is essential in understanding well-being. Conclusions: We highlight that the practice of using poorly validated measures hampers progress in understanding the relationship between the changing social environment and well-being. We conclude that different methods should be combined more often to reduce the participants’ burden and form a holistic perspective on the social environment.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Langener_JMIR.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Crisissignaleringsplan monitoren en visualiseren</title>
  <dc:creator>Massi Aoudjan, Elisa van Delft, Date van der Veen, Laura Bringmann, Gert Stulp, Barbara Montagne</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Aoudjan_gedragstherapie.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Crisissignaleringsplan monitoren en visualiseren</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Gedragstherapie</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Massi Aoudjan, Elisa van Delft, Date van der Veen, Laura Bringmann, Gert Stulp, Barbara Montagne</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="../../">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Patiënten met een borderline-persoonlijkheidsstoornis (BPS) zijn kwets- baar voor crises. Een crisissignaleringsplan (CSP) kan een crisis helpen voor- komen, maar voor het opstellen van een helpend CSP is inzicht nodig in de vroege signalen van een crisis. Dit inzicht ontbreekt vaak. Door gedurende een instabiele periode van de patiënt gebruik te maken van de experience sampling method (ESM) wordt persoonlijke en betrouw- bare informatie verzameld over de crisis, wat een goede basis kan zijn voor het opstellen van een CSP. In deze pilot onderzochten de auteurs de haal- baarheid en bruikbaarheid van deze methodiek. Het blijkt haalbaar te zijn om patiënten met BPS in een periode waarin er sprake is van een (dreigen- de) crisis driemaal daags een online vragenlijst in te laten vullen. De visuele terugkoppeling van de ESM-data aan de patiënt kan nieuwe en bruikbare inzichten opleveren in de onderliggende risicofactoren voor crisis. Bredere inzetbaarheid van de methodiek dient nader onderzocht te worden.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Aoudjan_gedragstherapie.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Fertility preferences in China in the twenty-first century</title>
  <dc:creator>Rui Lu, Anne Gauthier, Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Lu_JPR.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Fertility preferences in China in the twenty-first century</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Journal of Population Research</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Rui Lu, Anne Gauthier, Gert Stulp</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12546-023-09303-0">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>There is continuing debate on how low China’s fertility has reached and whether China has fallen into the “low fertility trap”. This paper addresses this debate by revisiting the trends in fertility preferences in the past decades in China based on a meta review. Moreover, the analysis contrasts distinct measurements of fertility preferences to capture different aspects of reproductive decision-making. This papers reviews 152 studies resulting in 137 estimates for the mean of preferred number of children, 104 estimates for the proportions of different numbers of children preferred and 66 estimates for the second-child preferences. We found that after the long-time decline of fertility preferences in the last century, the average family size remained at a low level but started to increase slowly since 2001. This upturn was observed for all three types of measurements of fertility preferences: ideal, desired, and planned family size. The results also indicate a strong two-child preference (more than 50% of respondents) in China, although 30% of people prefer one child and only a small fraction indicating an ideal family size for three or more children. Results on people’s preference for a second child were less consistent. We concluded that fertility is unlikely to increase rapidly in China even when the government adopts more relaxed family planning policy. Because the upward trend in fertility preferences was very minimal and the economic constraints will prevent many people to realise their preferences.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2023_Lu_JPR.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Collecting personal networks to study social influences on fertility behaviour</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_RESNET.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; NetResilience seminar</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Groningen, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://www.netresilience.fi/en/">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2023_NETresillience.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>People’s social environment is key in explaining their behaviour and preferences, including how many children people want and have. Unfortunately, obtaining information on the social environment, for instance through collecting personal network data, is difficult and often burdensome to participants. In this talk, I will first report on my experiences with collecting large personal network data (25 alters) from a representative sample of Dutch women. I’ll discuss the trade-offs researchers face when designing network studies between the burden to respondents and the reliability of characteristics of networks. Data quality is further discussed, including the usefulness of the concept “friend”. In the second part of the talk, I use these data to test evolutionary and sociological ideas about the breakdown of kin networks in contemporary populations as an explanation for the fertility decline. I’ll further discuss how personal network data can inform on social influences on fertility behaviour.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Fertility</category>
  <category>Networks</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_RESNET.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Collecting personal networks to study social influences on fertility behaviour</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_POPNET.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; POPNET Connects</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Amsterdam, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://www.popnet.io/events/">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2023_POPNET.pdf">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>People’s social environment is key in explaining their behaviour and preferences, including how many children people want and have. Unfortunately, obtaining information on the social environment, for instance through collecting personal network data, is difficult and often burdensome to participants. In this talk, I will first report on my experiences with collecting large personal network data (25 alters) from a representative sample of Dutch women. I’ll discuss the trade-offs researchers face when designing network studies between the burden to respondents and the reliability of characteristics of networks. Data quality is further discussed, including the usefulness of the concept “friend”. In the second part of the talk, I use these data to test evolutionary and sociological ideas about the breakdown of kin networks in contemporary populations as an explanation for the fertility decline. I’ll further discuss how personal network data can inform on social influences on fertility behaviour.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Fertility</category>
  <category>Networks</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2023_POPNET.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Understanding Narratives from Demographic Survey Data: a Comparative Study with Multiple Neural Topic Models</title>
  <dc:creator>Xiao Xu,Gert Stulp, Antal van der Bosch, Anne Gauthier</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2022_Xu_proceedings.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Understanding Narratives from Demographic Survey Data: a Comparative Study with Multiple Neural Topic Models</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-book" aria-label="book"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Conference proceedings of Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing</em></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-users" aria-label="users"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Xiao Xu,Gert Stulp, Antal van der Bosch, Anne Gauthier</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download manuscript <a href="../../pdf/2022_Xu.pdf">here</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Fertility intentions as verbalized in surveys are a poor predictor of actual fertility outcomes, the number of children people have. This can partly be explained by the uncertainty people have in their intentions. Such uncertainties are hard to capture through traditional survey questions, although open-ended questions can be used to get insight into people’s subjective narratives of the future that determine their intentions. An- alyzing such answers to open-ended questions can be done through Natural Language Process- ing techniques. Traditional topic models (e.g., LSA and LDA), however, often fail to do since they rely on co-occurrences, which are often rare in short survey responses. The aim of this study was to apply and evaluate topic models on demographic survey data. In this study, we applied neural topic models (e.g.&nbsp;BERTopic, CombinedTM) based on language models to responses from Dutch women on their fertil- ity plans, and compared the topics and their coherence scores from each model to expert judgments. Our results show that neural mod- els produce topics more in line with human interpretation compared to LDA. However, the coherence score could only partly reflect on this, depending on the method and corpus used for calculation. This research is important be- cause, first, it helps us develop more informed strategies on model selection and evaluation for topic modeling on survey data; and second, it shows that the field of demography has much to gain from adopting novel NLP methods.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/publications/2022_Xu_proceedings.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_pub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R workshop for teachers</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2022_Rworkshop.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; R workshop</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Grote Kruisstraat, Groningen, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="http://stulp.gmw.rug.nl/Rworkshop/">here</a> for website</p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>R workshop for teachers</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2022_Rworkshop.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using microsimulation, administrative data, and supercomputers to realistically model fertility behaviour: the case of fertility preferences and childlessness</title>
  <dc:creator>Gert Stulp</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2022_ODDISEI.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p><br> <i class="fa-solid fa-podcast" aria-label="podcast"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; ODISSEI conference</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-map-marker" aria-label="map-marker"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Utrecht, the Netherlands</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-window-maximize" aria-label="window-maximize"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Click <a href="https://odissei-data.nl/calendar/odissei-conference-for-social-science-in-the-netherlands-2022/">here</a> for website</p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-download" aria-label="download"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Download materials <a href="../../pdf/2022_ODISSEI_Gert Stulp.pdf">here</a></p>
<p><i class="fa-solid fa-video-camera" aria-label="video-camera"></i> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; There is a <a href="https://vimeo.com/769341726">video!</a></p>
</section>
<section id="description" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="description">Description</h2>
<p>Education is a strong driver of whether and when women become mothers. Many different and contradicting mechanisms have been proposed to explain why highly educated women are more likely to remain childless and become mothers at higher ages than less educated women. The demands on data to disentangle these mechanisms are extraordinary, and no dataset exists that allows for this. Microsimulation models can help in this situation by explicitly modelling the mechanisms and comparing the outcomes of the models to real-world outcomes. The simulation models presented here simulate fertility outcomes over the life courses of agents based on behavioural factors, such preferences and partnership trajectories, and biological factors that determine the ability to have children, such as the age at sterility, fecundability, and intrauterine mortality. To parametrise the models, we use administrative data from Social Statistics Netherlands, survey data from the LISS panel for the behavioural factors, and findings from reproductive medicine for the biological parameters. To estimate unknown parameters in the models (for which no data are available), we use Approximate Bayesian Computation. This is computationally rather demanding which is why we have used supercomputers. Our simulations reproduce the pattern of unintended childlessness strongly varying across women with different educational levels. Despite higher educated women preferring to have children at a later age, our simulations showed that these preferences hardly played a role in explaining childlessness. The higher age at cohabitation was the main explanation for the higher unintended childlessness among highly educated women. We discuss how these models can be used to explain the surprising reversal in gradient between education and fertility that is observed in Scandinavian countries. We end by discussing the advantages and drawbacks of our simulation approach and how it can contribute to family sociology</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Talk</category>
  <category>Fertility</category>
  <category>Simulation</category>
  <guid>https://www.gertstulp.com/research/talks/2022_ODDISEI.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.gertstulp.com/images/new_event.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="97" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
